A Guide to the Papers of Henry Clay, 1798-1934, n.d.
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Series I: Correspondence and Documents
  - Henry Clay, Washington, to Robert R. Henry, Albany, New York 1824 January 14, ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf. Endorsed by Henry. #3472. (Box-folder 1:50)
    Clay has received Henry's letter "in relation to certain alleged malpractices of officers of Government." Clay replies that "if they exist in the degree and extent to which you suppose they ought to be seriously investigated and the proper remedy applied." He "can only present to the House over which I have the honor to preside any petition which shall be respectfully couched, and transmitted to me for presentation."
  - Henry Clay, Ashland, to B.[enjamin] W.[atkins] Leigh, Richmond, Virginia. 1824 July 31, ALS, 3 pp. Endorsed by Leigh. #1395. (Box-folder 1:51)
    Clay thanks Leigh for "communicating the very satisfactory result of the action for Euphraim" and asks Leigh to have Mr. [Garland] Tinsley or Col. [Lawson] Burfoot to arrange "to rent out the property for this year." Clay then discusses the "occupying claimant laws" in some detail and concludes with greetings to Mrs. Leigh and Mrs. [John] Wickham.
  - Henry Clay, Washington, to B.[enjamin] W.[atkins] Leigh, Richmond, Virginia. 1824 December 14, ALS, 1 p.; docketed by [Leigh?] on blank leaf, now detached. #1395. (Box-folder 1:52)
    Clay replies to Leigh's request "to know the state of Kentucky politics." Clay is "sorry to be obliged to tell you that I derive very little satisfaction from the contemplation of them." Clay briefly discusses the Relief and Anti-Relief parties and the possible abolition of the Kentucky Court of Appeals. He encloses a check for $50 for prosecution of his suit regarding Euphraim.
  - Henry Clay, Ashland, to Littleton Dennis Teackle, Annapolis, Maryland 1825 January 24, ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf. #2388. (Box-folder 1:53)
    Clay responds to the "bill" Teackle sent him [not present] and does not think the "project it proposes" will succeed. Clay states that the "emission of paper, founded upon any other basis than that of specie cannot...under any conceivable circumstances, be attended with success." He notes that "[o]ur paper bank in Kentucky [Bank of the Commonwealth] has so far disappointed the hopes of the public that every body is tired of it and desirous to get back, as soon as we can, to a specie circulation."
  - Henry Clay, Washington, to James Strong 1825 March 29, ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; printed biography of Clay from unidentified source laid down on address leaf. #2933-b. (Box-folder 1:54)
    Clay tells Strong "in confidence" that since Mr. Clinton has declined to accept the "English Mission," it has been offered to Mr. R.[ufus] King. Clay states that King's "weight of character, the estimate in which he is held both here and in England, his residence, and the place of his nativity, so deeply concerned in fixing our N.E. boundary" will be "sufficient considerations for his appointment." Clay has directed a copy of his [March 26, 1825] address to his constituents to be sent to Strong.
  - Henry Clay, Washington, to General [Joseph Vance] 1825 April 19, ALS, 1 p.; mounted on board. #4602-a. (Box-folder 1:55)
    Clay thanks Vance for his recent letter and states that the "information which it communicates is very gratifying." Vance's friend Josiah Baldwin "has been provided for as you wished." Clay says that he does "not find my new office a bed of roses. I work from 12 to 14 hours per day."
  - Legal document, signed by Henry Clay as Secretary of State 1825 April 28, DS, 1 p.; partially printed. #1754-b. (Box-folder 1:56)
    Document asserting that Richard Peters is and was "a Judge of the United States for the District of Pennsylvania" and that R.C. Weightman, a witness for Robert S. Garnett and Olympia Garnett is and was the mayor of Washington, D.C.
  - Henry Clay, Wheeling, to James Barbour, Washington 1825 May 22, ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf. #38-144. (Box-folder 1:57)
    Clay will, in one hour, "be on a steam boat for Kentucky." He was "received with enthusiasm on this side of the mountains," and "every species of kind and considerate attention have manifested the good feelings which prevail respecting" him. He mentions that Lafayette was "at Lexington on the 16th" and "is expected here in four or five days. The steamboat, on which he ascended the Ohio, sank below Louisville in the night, to the great personal hazard of the passengers, but without any loss of life." Clay asks Barbour to "make my respectful compliments to the President and our Colleagues."
  - Henry Clay, Ashland, to Matthew Carey, Philadelphia 1825 June 6, ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; docketed by Carey; postmarked Lexington Jun. 7. #1754-b. (Box-folder 1:58)
    Clay has received Carey's letter containing "the Copies of your papers containing an examination of the later British doctrines as have been unfolded by Mr. [William] Huskisson, in their new policy." Clay has "put your valuable papers in a course of distribution."
  - Henry Clay, Washington, to J[ohn] E. Hall 1825 September 29, ALS, 1 p. With engraving of Clay from unidentified source mounted beneath his signature. #5825. (Box-folder 1:59)
    Clay thanks Hall for his letter informing Clay of Hall's intent to "to continue the life of Lafayette, began [sic] by Mr. Waln." Clay does not wish to make any changes to his address of December 10, 1824, which Hall wishes to include in the book.
  - Henry Clay, Washington, to James Brown 1827 May 30, ALS, 3 pp. #991, Tracy W. McGregor Library. (Box-folder 1:60)
    Clay "shall send you in a few days, a long instruction on the subject of our claims" against France. Approximately one-half of the letter consists of instructions to Brown. "On American politics" Clay is confident that Mr. [John Quincy] Adams will be re-elected and "that we shall have a most embittered contest, uncomfortable in all respects; and that the struggle in Kentucky will be hot and sharp." Clay mentions "[o]ur affair at Rio Janiero [sic]" and says it is "not likely to lead to any serious consequences." He mentions that the Clays are more comfortable by their "removal to Decatur's house." He encloses two volumes of his speeches, one for Brown and one to be "neatly bound and presented in my name to Genl. La Fayette." His daughter Anne is unable to spend the summer since she is "in a family way."
  - Henry Clay, Lexington, to Col. G[eorge] Thompson, Pleasantfield, Mercer [County, Ky.] 1827 July 13, ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf. #7100.
    Clay returns Mr. [Claiborne W.?] Gooch's letter [not present] and states that it has "several errors respecting me." Clay states that he did not refuse to serve in "Mr. [James] Monroe's Cabinet, because Mr. [John Quincy] Adams was a member of it."
  - Henry Clay, Washington, to H[ezekiah] Niles 1827 November 5, ALS, 1 p. #2933-a. (Box-folder 1:61)
    Clay has received Niles' letter with "Copies of the Address in behalf of the Harrisburg Convention" and has no doubt he will "find in it an able exposition of facts and views in support of the American System." Clay mentions Mr. Markeley and Mr. Buchanan.
  - Henry Clay, Washington, to Mrs. S[tephen] Decatur (Susan Wheeler) 1827 November 25, ALS, 1 p.; with attached blank leaf. #1087. (Box-folder 1:62)
    Clay thanks Mrs. Decatur for her letter and urges her to attend a "diplomatic dinner on friday next." She "would promote greatly the happiness" of her friends and herself "by occasionally mixing in our circles."
  - Henry Clay, Washington, to James Brown 1828 May 17, ALS, 3 pp. #991, Tracy W. McGregor Library. (Box-folder 1:63)
    Clay expresses concern over the accounts of "Mrs. Brown's health." Clay re-states his opinion that "Mr. Adams will be re-elected"; his opinion "excludes for our calculation Pennsa. Virginia and the other Southern States, which I think cannot be relied on for Mr. Adams, although there are hopes of the two States mentioned and North Carolina." Clay mentions money owed to Brown, the Louisiana treaty with France and treaties with "Prussia and the Hanse towns." Clay states that there "is no present danger of any rupture with G. Britain about our N. Eastern boundary. It is to be arbitrated." He concludes by asking Brown to purchase gloves for Mrs. Clay.
  - Henry Clay, Washington, to James Barbour 1828 May 29, ALS, 1 p. Imperfect; large portions of text wanting; silked. (Box-folder 1:64)
    #38-144.Letter of appointment as ambassador to the United Kingdom.
  - Henry Clay, Washington, to James Barbour 1828 May 29, ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; portion of text and address leaf torn away; docketed by Barbour. #38-144. (Box-folder 1:65)
    Clay introduces Mr. Gerard H. Coster of New York, who will be traveling to Europe "for the purpose of amusement and instruction."
  - Henry Clay, Washington 1828 June 14, DS, 1 p. Printed. #2908. (Box-folder 1:66)
    Printed circular, transmitting 110 copies "of the Laws of the last session of Congress" to the Governor of Mississippi.
  - Henry Clay, Cuckooville, to Murray Morris 1828 September 27, ALS, 2 pp.; with attached address leaf. #38-79. (Box-folder 1:67)
    Clay had intended to visit Morris on his "return from the Springs to Washington," but "had some how confounded your residence and Louisa Courthouse, which I supposed were situated within a short distance of each other." Clay asks Murray to visit him in Washington and asks if he was "serious about purchasing my grey horses."
  - Henry Clay, Washington, to James Madison 1828 October 10, ALS, 1 p.; negative photostat. #2933-e. (Box-folder 1:68)
    "Confidential" in Clay's hand, following salutation. Clay has heard "through a respected channel" that "it would conduce greatly to the comfort of Mrs. Randolph [Martha Jefferson Randolph], the daughter of Mr. Jefferson, if her son in law, Mr. Trist [Nicholas P. Trist] were appointed to some Clerkship in one of the Departments here." Clay can provide a position for Trist if he were assured that "Mr. Trist possesses the requisite qualifications."
  - Henry Clay, Washington, to James Brown 1828 October 11, ALS. 2 pp.; with attached blank leaf. #911. (Box-folder 1:69)
    Clay comments on the health of Mrs. Brown and hopes that "her judicious retirement to the delightful gardens of Versailles may restore her health." He comments at length on the presidential election. Elections in Maryland and Delaware have just closed, and the election in Kentucky was close. Still, Clay believes Adams will carry Kentucky and "he should also received 20 votes in N. York." He mentions that "the violence in the South is pretty much limited to So. Carolina & Georgia. It derives no countenance and will obtain no support in Virginia, which is rapidly becoming a Tariff state." Clay authorizes Brown to compensate "Mr. B." [W. Armand Barnet] "who acted as Secretary." He mentions that the "King of the Netherlands has been selected" to arbitrate the border dispute between the United States and Great Britain. He closes by stating that the "country is generally prosperous. Kentucky is becoming quite so. Virginia and some of the Southern States are exceptions."
  - Henry Clay, Washington, to Dr. J.[ames] M. Morris 1828 October 25, ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf. #38-79. (Box-folder 1:70)
    Morris's "manager arrived this morning and is preparing to start with the horses." Clay describes the horses as a "most serviceable pair." He invites Morris and his wife to visit in Washington and jokingly addresses Morris's concerns that "Mrs. M. may be infected by political heresies."
  - Nicholas P. Trist, to Henry Clay 1828 [November 29], ALS, 4 pp.; docketed "Dec. 1828." #1727. (Box-folder 1:71)
    Trist understands that Clay may have an incorrect understanding of his recent connection with the pro-Jackson Charlottesville, Va. Virginia Advocate. In a lengthy statement, Trist attempts to correct the misunderstanding and notes that he had reluctantly accepted a position as editor mainly because of the salary involved.
  - Henry Clay, Washington, to James Barbour 1828 December 29, ALS, 3 pp.; silked. #38-144. (Box-folder 1:72)
    Clay tells Barbour that "General Jackson is elected by a majority of more than two thirds of the Electors. We were beaten in all the doubtful States, without exception... The President has borne his reverse with much philosophic composure and our friends, generally, are less affected than I feared they would be." Clay mentions that there is "vague speculation as to the intentions of the President elect. His own friends even do not appear to know what they are." He says that the current session of Congress has been very quiet and the "Jackson party will probably remain quiet for the present." He mentions the Senate's delay in confirming Mr. Hughs as ambassador to the Netherlands and Mr. [John Jordan] Crittenden to the Supreme Court. Clay closes by saying he will "return to Kentucky upon the close of the present administration, and whether I shall take any part in public affairs hereafter, I shall then decide."
  - Henry Clay to "My dear friend" 1829 January 2, ALS, 1 p. #3888. (Box-folder 1:73)
    Clay proposes a visit "if I thought you would receive me."
  - Henry Clay, Washington, to Dr. J.[ames] M. Morris 1829 January 8, ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf. #39-79. (Box-folder 1:74)
    Clay thanks Morris for the gift of "a dozen bacon hams" and states they "fully sustained the antient and renowned character of Virginia hams." He closes by expressing Mrs. Clay's desire to have the directions used for preparing the hams.
  - Henry Clay, Ashland, to Thomas Law 1829 May 28, ALS, 2 pp. #2801. (Box-folder 1:75)
    Clay discusses a land title case in Kentucky and refers Law to Mr. [George W.] Bibb. Clay then talks about the "picture of public affairs at Washington." He states that the "smoak of the cannon, fired in exultation of the Election of President Jackson, has hardly yet vanished. Mortification and pride prevent many from expressing their regrets and disappointments, on account of their having supported him." Clay states "many have taken the first step towards weaning themselves from their infuriated attachment, and returning to common Sense." He concludes that Law has done well to retire from Washington "to enjoy the tranquil scenes of rural life, in spite of all the wickedness, violence, and hypocrisy which at present disgrace the Metropolis."
  - Henry Clay, Ashland, to James F. Conover 1829 November 22, ALS, 2 pp.; with attached address leaf; postmarked Lexington, Dec. 25. #4475. (Box-folder 1:76)
    Clay comments on Conover's idea of starting a new newspaper in Cincinnati. Clay points out that no newspaper can "permanently succeed which does not abstain from any violation of public decorum in its discussions, make truth its guide, and avoid personality" and that no place "in the Western Country is so important for diffusing intelligence to the people as Cincinnati." Clay says he will subscribe to Conover's newspaper but cannot invest in it. He hopes there will be no "competition or collision" between Conover and Charles Hammond.
  - Henry Clay, Ashland, to E.C. Berry 1829 November 30, ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; postmarked Lexington. #2933-c. (Box-folder 1:77)
    Clay writes to Berry, Auditor of Public Accounts, Vandalia, Illinois, to confirm that his "lands in your State have been placed in a situation free from danger of being sold for taxes." He asks if his arrangement to pay land taxes from a previous overpayment is still in effect.
  - Henry Clay, Ashland, to James F. Conover 1830 May 1, ALS, 3 pp. #4475-a. (Box-folder 1:78)
    Clay comments on Conover's newspaper and states that although it "has not been patronized to the extent you expected" in Kentucky, when the paper is more generally known, Conover will not be disappointed. Clay mentions the possibility of a "Northern trip" but has rejected the idea lest his motive be questioned. He states that the "information which reaches me from all quarters but especially from Washington City, as to my future prospects, is in a high degree encouraging." He does not know what "effect will be produced by the recent movements at Harrisburg and Albany" but says that "those movements are mere stratagems of Mr. V. Buren" [Martin Van Buren]. Clay goes on to discuss Van Buren's "notorious embicility and incompetency, as well as his maladministration." Clay mentions Judge John McLean. He concludes by discussing the recent Jefferson Day dinner in Washington, which "indicates the course of attack on the Tariff and Internal Improvements."
  - Henry Clay, Ashland, to James F. Conover 1830 May 1, ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l. #4475-a. (Box-folder 1:79)
    Clay thanks Conover for his letter and says that while he has "entertained thoughts of a Northern trip," he is now "disinclined" to make such a trip. He says that the "information which reaches me from all quarters ... as to my future prospects, is in a high degree encouraging." Clay mentions Martin Van Buren's "strategems" against John C. Calhoun. Clay states that he has never wronged Judge John McLean and, along with other friends of John Quincy Adams, regrets the Judge's "course during the late Admin." He discusses the tariff and internal improvements and says "it is fortunate that we now know the plan of the Campaign of our opponents, and we ought now to prepare ours to defeat it." Clay states, possibly in reference to the Maysville veto, that "the sacrifice of our American System is to propitiate G. Britain as well as the South."
  - Henry Clay, Ashland, to George W. Featherstonhaugh 1830 May 23, ALS, 2 pp.; with attached address leaf; postmarked Lexington May 24. #2933-d. (Box-folder 1:80)
    Clay thanks Featherstonhaugh for his letter and mentions that he spent "some very pleasant days" in New Orleans with Stephen Van Rensselaer. He finds "great benefit as well as amusement in my agricultural pursuits" and "shall be ready very soon to renounce for ever the strife and the cares of public life." Clay states that the election of "Genl. Jackson ought to be regarded as an exception from the general good sense with which the American people have conducted their affairs." Clay concludes by sending "warmest regards and my best wishes for his happiness and prosperity" to Baron Paul de Krudener.
  - Henry Clay, Ashland, to John C. Wright 1830 May 31, ALS, 2 pp.; with attached address leaf; docketed; postmarked Lexington Jun.1. #5903. (Box-folder 1:81)
    Clay comments on Wright's plan to run for the House of Representatives from Ohio and says that "it would be very gratifying to friends of our cause." Clay states that the "general results of the present Session of Congress are highly favorable to our cause." He mentions Samuel A. Foot and John Holmes. There is a brief discussion of the tariff and Clay concludes by speculating on whether or not the "President has approved the Maysville [Road] appropriation."
  - Henry Clay, Ashland, to James F. Conover 1830 June 13, ALS, 2 pp.; with attached address leaf; postmarked Lexington. #4475-a. (Box-folder 1:82)
    Clay suggests that the Constitution be amended to allow "a bare majority of all the Members elected to each house of Congress, instead of two thirds of a quorum...to pass a bill returned by the President." He also discusses "the Indian bill" which he says "threatens to bring a foul and lasting stain upon the good faith, humanity and character of the nation." He concludes by asking Conover to consult with Charles Hammond and Isaiah Thomas.
  - Henry Clay, Ashland, to James F. Conover 1830 August 16, ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; postmarked Lexington Aug. 18. #4475-a. (Box-folder 1:83)
    Clay has sent to William Greene "a Sketch of my Speech delivered at Cincinnati" and refers Conover to Daniel Drake concerning its possible publication. Clay concludes by saying the "news from Indiana, Illinois and, Missouri...is highly encouraging."
  - Henry Clay, Ashland, to James F. Conover 1830 October 31, ALS, 2 pp.; with attached address leaf and Clay's seal; postmarked Lexington. #4475-a. (Box-folder 1:84)
    Clay expresses "lively interest" in the success of the Cincinnati American. He says that the Kentucky Convention will be held on December 9th in Frankfort. Clay suggests that Conover prepare a "subscription paper" to be circulated at the Convention. Clay comments on the Ohio and Pennsylvania elections and closes with the question "Who is your Senator?"
  - Henry Clay, Ashland, to John L. Lawrence 1830 December 13, ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; docketed; postmarked Lexington, Dec. 14. #5828, Tracy W. McGregor Library. (Box-folder 1:85)
    "Confidential" in Clay's hand following salutation. Clay refers to Lawrence's letter of the 2nd and says that he does not disapprove of the measures Lawrence referred to. Rather, he is "perfectly persuaded that without some such defeat awaits us in N. York at least in 1832." He mentions that the Kentucky Convention met and the proceedings "were marked by harmony and vigor." Barton [?] was not put forward as a candidate and the Benton candidate was defeated. The legislature has not elected a Senator because "some half dozen of our friends have persuaded themselves or been persuaded by others that they are pledged, on the particular question of a Senator to work for one of the Jackson party." Clay closes by saying he is leaving for New Orleans on "private affairs exclusively."
  - Henry Clay, New Orleans, to John L. Lawrence 1831 March 7, ALS, 2 pp.; with attached address leaf; postmarked New Orleans, Mar.7. #5828, Tracy W. McGregor Library. (Box-folder 1:86)
    "Confidential" in Clay's hand, following salutation. Clay states that he believes "we shall be able to rescue the Government from the dangers which are impending over it." He considers "the election of any particular individual to the Chief Magistracy so perfectly a consideration of secondary and subordinate consequence, compared to the great and patriotic object of preserving all that is valuable in our institutions that I am entirely ready to surrender my pretensions, whatever they may be, to any one who can unite our friends and hold out a more encouraging prospect of success." He closes saying he will leave New Orleans "in the course of the week" and regrets that he feels unable to make a campaign visit to New York.
  - John L. Lawrence, New York, to Henry Clay 1831 March 29, ALS, 3 pp.; with attached address leaf. #6683. (Box-folder 1:87)
    Lawrence writes in response to Clay's letter of March 7 and says in regard to "your frank declaration of willingness to yield your own pretensions in favor of others, I must be equally frank in Saying, that to your numerous friends, here Such an avowal, publickly made, would not be acceptable." He goes on to say that "our friends look with great anxiety to the next election in your State" and that there are some "expectations of a Jackson triumph in that quarter." Lawrence closes by discussing "an attack" against Robert W. Wickliffe in relation to his affairs with Robert Scott.
  - Henry Clay, Ashland, to James Brown 1831 April 8, ALS, 2 pp.; with attached address leaf. #991, Tracy W. McGregor Library. (Box-folder 1:88)
    Clay reports that he arrived in Lexington from New Orleans on April 6 and comments on the weather and the health of family members. He has learned from Mr. Senator [Josiah S.] Johnson that "Mr. Calhoun will be a candidate for the Presidency, and that he will probably obtain the vote of S. Carolina, No. Carolina and Virginia." Clay has "not yet seen evidence sufficient to convince me of its correctness."
  - Henry Clay, Ashland, to Jabez D. Hammond 1831 April 13, ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; docketed; postmarked Lexington Apr.15. #2529. (Box-folder 1:89)